Guide to the Leah Dyjak photographs, 2014-2018 RL.11695
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leah Dyjak photographs
2014-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dyjak, Leah, 1981-
RL.11695
1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 25 color inkjet prints 16 x 20 inches
Collection comprises twenty-five 16x20 inch color inkjet prints from a body of work titled "New Beach" by artist Leah Dyjak. The images, taken by Dyjak on the Atlantic coast, show ocean and sand encroaching on and destroying human-made barriers and boundaries - roads, jetties, and groins - with people looking on, stretching out, and strolling the beaches, evoking the nature of human existence at the liminal boundaries of water and land. This work received the 2018 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of Environmental Change. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Arranged in original order as assigned by the photographer.
Biographical Note
Leah Dyjak is an interdisciplinary, lens-based artist splitting her time between New York and Massachusetts. She received her MFA from the University of Texas at Austin. Her site-specific work combines performance, labor, film, and photography to explore how generations of human use affect the ecologies of place. Her images and installations often push the edges of the photographic frame. Her work plays with our perceptions of perceived boundaries and charts matter in flux. Leah is an Assistant Professor of Video and Photography at Winthrop University and summer faculty at the Anderson Ranch. Her work has been shown at Flex Space, Pump Project and Blue Star Contemporary in Texas and throughout the Northeast. She is represented by the Schoolhouse Gallery in Provincetown Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Provenance
The Leah Dyjak photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The photographs in this collection were printed at Winthrop University Creator Space on Moab Entrada Rag paper, using an Epson SC-8000 printer and Archival Epson ink.
Content Description
Collection comprises twenty-five color inkjet prints from a body of work titled New Beach by artist Leah Dyjak. The images, taken by Dyjak on the Atlantic coast, show ocean and sand encroaching on and destroying human-made barriers and boundaries - roads, jetties, and groins - as people look on, stretch out, or stroll on the beach, evoking the nature of existence at the liminal boundaries of water and land.
From the artist's statement: "Conceivably, the ocean contains all time and all places, with the coastline delineating where the understood meets the unfathomable. It acts as a boundary, the line between where we walk and where we float. Standing at the edge is a way to become physically close to our point of origin — geologically, biologically, metaphysically. It is the terra incognita of the modern world. With every crash of a wave, the line of the coast as we know it changes; our data becomes obsolete instantaneously. Water changes state, weather changes everything."
The prints measure 16x20 inches and are all horizontally oriented. This work received the 2018 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of Environmental Change. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Beach erosion -- Photographs; Beaches -- Photographs; Coast changes -- Atlantic Coast (U.S.); Landscape photography; Liminality; People and nature -- Pictorial works; Atlantic Coast (U.S.) -- Photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Dyjak, Leah, 1981-
- New Beach, 2014-2018
  - New beach, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0001)
  - Right whales, 2014; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0002)
  - Sea anchors, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0003)
  - Holy stone, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0004)
  - Founder, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0005)
  - Absolve, 2018; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0006)
  - Ballast, 2016; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0007)
  - Larson C, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0008)
  - Coastliners, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0009)
  - Take a knee, 2018; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0010)
  - Precipice, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0011)
  - Sandy fist, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0012)
  - Fallen, 2018; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0013)
  - Cleave, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0014)
  - Fissure, 2016; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0015)
  - Awash, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0016)
  - Witness, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0017)
  - Beached, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0018)
  - Swimmers, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0019)
  - All hands, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0020)
  - Sea trial, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0021)
  - Figure head, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0022)
  - Hope sail, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0023)
  - Magnetic north, 2017; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0024)
  - Echo sound, 2018; 16 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11695-P-0025)